hello and welcome it is August 12th
2024 and we are in active math stream
number
1111111111 and with repeat friend Toby
SMI today we're going to talk about
structured active inference there will
be a presentation followed by a
discussion so thank you Toby for joining
and everybody for watching and asking
questions and looking forward to
learning more here so go for it cool
great thanks Daniel thanks for having me
on again um so as as Daniel says this is
going to be a talk about structured Act
of inference which is really um my
account of the structure of active
inference systems and really it kind of
extends Beyond Act of inference um to
any kind of system that you could think
of as as being kind of aent
and that has some kind of compositional
structure in particular but we'll get
we'll get to that okay um the way I like
to begin thinking about structure of and
act inference is at the moment it's it's
kind of like if you wanted to model in
active inference uh an agent or a person
getting onto a bicycle or getting into a
car then I think as things stand it
might be a bit tricky because that
process involves like changing the
agent's Mark of blanket or how I like to
think of it is changing the agent's
interface and to be able to talk about
that precisely you need to have a good
notion of what interface is so you know
you as you're you know getting into the
getting onto the bike let's say you move
you change from you know walking by
taking steps one after another to you
know um like change your direction by
like leaning and and pedaling so that
kind of type of actions you can take and
the things that you pay attention to
change yes because you're now this kind
of composite system you and the bicycle
and it's a similar story when you get
into the car um so that that really that
means that you don't just have like one
like set of observations and like one
set of actions you can take this this
kind of composing process means that you
have to have a bit more flexibility and
in particular you need to say precisely
what those sets of observations and sets
of actions should be
so the basic idea behind struct
structured active inference is really
just to put the ideas of active
inference into categorical systems
theory and so categorical systems theory
is just an account of how dynamical
systems of very general kind um yeah are
made up of parts and how those parts
composed together and it separates out
the notion of the system from the notion
of its interface and so this allows us
to be very precise about what is the
kind of agent markup blanket and how
does that change so the we inherit kind
of number of features of categorical
systems theory in this notion of
structured active inference in
particular we inherit this kind of idea
of structured interface and that means
not only do we have to be precise about
what the interfaces are but we also are
able to say what the structure in some
sense of the interface is and how does
it change and how does it you know
interact with other kinds of
interface I'll say a lot more about that
in the next few
slides um because categorical systems
theory is all about the composition of
systems and their interfaces so is
structured active inference and that
means that we get a a nice kind of um
modular account of active inference and
we can compare active inference with
other accounts of agency and we can
compare active inference systems of
various different kinds in a nice
precise way and so that means we
could sort of uh translate between
continuous Time and discret Time systems
or various different kinds of continuous
time or stochastic systems those are all
different systems theories of their own
and active inference has lots to say
about how to do
um inference and policy selection on
those different kinds of systems but C
categorical systems theory means that
we're very precise about what what those
different systems and how that inference
process
works and so this this kind of
comparability comes into um is is
formalized by the notion of morphism of
systems so this these morphisms are they
come in s of two kinds in systems theory
we get morphisms of interface um those
are the things that allow you to sort of
plug yourself into another sort of
bigger system in some sense that is as
you get onto the car you sort of get
onto the bicycle you're sort of wiring
yourself into this composite human
bicycle system but they also these
morphisms they also Encompass changing
the model that is changing the model of
system but also changing an individual
model itself so doing things like
structure learning parameter change so
normal learning um you know meta
learning or things that we might think
of in Neuroscience as effective
connectivity these are all kinds of
morphism of system and so this all of
this stuff comes out of packaging active
inference into this categorical systems
theory language
so with this we gain a lot of things not
only do we sort inherit these features
but we gain sort of some nice new
capabilities as well so I've already
talked about what we get from structured
interfaces um so that means that we get
systems where you can like the the kinds
of actions you take might depend on the
situation or context or mode that you're
in or that can act on very sort of
precisely defined structured interfaces
like computer apis
um we get Notions of agents that manage
agents in a precise compositional way or
sort of meta agents that can use active
inference itself to change their
structure there seems to be an
interesting link between um structure
learning as in within one model and and
planning as in choosing your sort of
policy your series of actions both of
those seem to be about composing
sequences of
morphisms and another thing that comes
out of um putting activ inference into
the language of categorical systems
theory is that we can also make contact
with categorical logic which can also be
applied to categorical systems theory
and that means that we can do things
like or you know we in principle can do
things like specify systems goals as
logical predicates um talk about uh
contracts that might have to hold
between agents or um or sort of uh on
their behaviors that you might you might
something you might care about if you're
interested in safety of artificial
intelligences um and this logic because
it's in this systems theoretic framework
has to be compatible with the patterns
of interaction of the systems now I'm
not going to say very much about this
because it's really quite a big and open
problem like spelling out all of the
details here but I've got a couple of
slides at the end about it um and in in
that same kind of vein and similar to
this notion of um policies as kind of
being sequences of morphisms um
structured Act of inference because we
uh give some kind of typing or context
information to the actions that are
available that means that we can do
things like type checking in principle
on policies and that's a kind of
rudimentary way to verify the safety of
a policy I.E just that it makes
sense so the basic um idea of
categorical systems theory um this is
the math stream so I'm going to be quite
mathematical here um so there are two
ingredients as I mentioned one is that
we have
a category of interfaces so that is just
something something very syntactic it
says okay here are the the interfaces
and Mark of blankets of all my different
systems um and and that those those
interfaces form the object of this
category and then here are all the ways
that these in interfaces could sort of
link up or connect and these these um
wirings um they become the morphisms of
this category of
interfaces um but there's information in
the category of
interfaces about the systems themselves
it's really just a sort of syntactic
gadget for talking about how things
connect up and so to to attach systems
to interfaces we have what's known as an
index category so we have for each
possible interface there's a whole
category of systems that might somehow
like fill that interface with a system
so we think of the interface as like a
box and then the the index category of
systems over that category of interfaces
fills that box with an actual system it
sort of brings it to life and it being
indexed category means that this um
these categories of systems over
interfaces have to be compatible with
the wiring up so if you have an
interface one box and another box side
by side and you connect them together
using one of the morphisms you're also
able to connect the systems in in this
way compatibly that is you know once
you've plugged your boxes together the
system sort of interacting this way
accordingly um so that allows us to do
this kind of um connection of systems um
it's not normally just a category we
also typically have what's known as the
monoidal structure on the category of
interfaces and that means that we can
place systems side by side we don't just
plug systems like one into another we
can have like two systems next to each
other and then sort of connect them into
a bigger system that is like you know
your body is made of lots of lots of
cells next to each other but they're all
sort of interconnected in
and that's that's sort of um um
formalized by this monoidal structure
which is sometimes called tensor and
represented with this symbol here and so
the systems theory again has to be
compatible with this tensor which means
if you put two boxes side by side and
systems in them then you also get a
system in the sort of composite like
double box system and so to do wiring
really often what happens is you have
one box I've written it as P here and
another box written as P Prime you put
them together into this P10 of P Prime
that means that you can connect these a
system over this and a system over this
into a system over the joint interface
and then say you've got some some wiring
so wiring would be a morphism p tensor P
Prime to Q then the systems theory
allows you to take that wiring and wire
the systems together accordingly and
then you that means you've got a system
on this like VI interface and so often
you see diagrams and systems theory it
to a bit like this this is p this is p
Prime this is q and then this is like
some like way of wiring the systems
together and then this is you know this
is your wiring and then you've got the
Sy and they you get you get a sort of
composite system like this so I've gone
very fast this is the basics of categor
categorical systems theory it's as I say
it's a it's a language for talking about
building complex systems from their
parts in a nice sort of formal
compositional mathematical way and so
what we're going to do is put active
inference into this language in a way
that generalizes active inference in
this sort of quite big New Direction
that allows for things like mode
dependence of actions and so to do that
I want to introduce a particular
category of interfaces um the category
of polinomial
functors um you if you know the work of
David spivac and his colleagues he's a
big proponent of this category for
talking about things like systems and
Dynamics and so I'm going to adopt his
notation um in talk about this category
um he calls it poly and there's a nice
book about this by David and um Nelson
new that you can read it's freely
available
online so a polinomial it's really again
as I say it's like a syntactic gadget
for talking about the interface of a
system and it has kind of two key
ingredients and it's really just like a
polinomial that you see in high school
algebra so it has like a set of summand
which are these like white the something
things and they're indexed by this P of
one set this is a set and each each sum
and has another set attached to it which
is the exponent so it's really just like
you know y^2 + 3 y + 1 um this is a
polinomial and you know we could tell
this could be like sum over i y to the x
i if you sort of you know if we think of
the three y as like y + y +
Y and so this is a sort of General
representation of a polinomial and we
think of the the indexing set p of1 as
the set of the uh of a set of the
systems outputs or the configurations
that it could adopt or in active
inference language like the observable
states of a generative
model and then for each possible
configuration of the system as I say you
have this set which represents the
inputs or the actions that a system
might take in that corresponding
configuration and so that's just what
how we think of a polinomial um and then
there are some things you can do with
polinomial in particular there's one
like trivial polinomial one that has
just sort of one configuration and one
possible input so there's no possible
variation in its configurations and no
interesting actions that it can take um
we can put polinomial like side by side
using this ten of product and this has
the kind of expected effect on the Pol
uh a configuration of a tensor is like a
configuration of each part and an input
is or an action is a an action or an
input of the corresponding parts like
that and mathematically we can translate
between this kind of
polinomial representation and what's
known as a a bundle which is just a
function so these are all sets the P of
I and the P of one and so we can do the
co-product or disjoint Union of these
sets by summing over the eyes and this
means that the elements of this big set
here are pairs of an eye an indexing I
in P of one and an element of the
corresponding uh exponent set and this
bundle is just a function that Maps iix
down to
I and this is uh useful for set for
defining the morphisms of polinomial
which will do the things that I think of
as wiring and I'll talk about that in a
moment but before I do so I want to um
introduce one important example of
polinomial which are the monomials
because they don't have interesting um
they don't have many interesting sort of
uh non-trivial summand they're just like
one term so and we write these as o y to
the A and these are going to be familiar
because they capture the kind of
classical Act of inference so here I
think of the O as like the set of
observations as an of an agent and the
exponent a as the set of actions and so
these actions are like the inputs to a
generative model that makes it
transition and the observations are like
the sort of the the sort of data that
the generative model or the environment
produces that the agent receives and
this is a polinomial because you're just
summing over the a the O's and for each
o you have the same a and the bundle
just takes a pair of o a and projects
down to
O Okay cool so let me talk about how
these things sort of wire up briefly um
these this this is done using the
morphisms of
pols which are otherwise known as
dependent lenses if you know about um
functional programming for instance so a
morphism is going to represent taking a
system and putting inside a bigger
system that is like if you've got two
small boxes and you wi them together to
biger to build a big box um or you take
two cells and you put or take multiple
cells and you put them together to sort
of make a multi cellular organism so if
we've got polinomial p and Q a morphism
from P to Q is given by two things um
one sort of goes forwards from P to q
and one sort of goes backwards and the
forward One S of takes the outputs of
the inner systems and turns them into an
output of the big system and the
backwards one takes the inputs to the
big system and the outputs of the inner
systems and uses them to produce inputs
to the small systems so like one of them
sort of goes from inside the box to the
out that's the the the f one map and
then the other one sort of goes in um
but it might take into account the sort
of internal inputs as well so it can be
used for like feedback so that is to say
we've got this um outputs map so we take
outputs of the inner box to the outer
box and for the corresponding
inputs in the outer box so that's these
y's we go backwards but we have to
account for this like mode dependence
which is a bit sort of funky but this
just says that if we've got an output
corresponding to position or
configuration I of the inner box then
we're allowed to look at the inputs that
correspond to the corresponding output
and then we sort of back propagate those
to the inputs again in configuration I
so there's a bit of sort of accounting
um you have to do to keep track of these
like the the sort of um of the
configurations of all the systems but
that just means that you know there's
some like mode dependence or some like
you know you might have some if you
think of the sort of multicellular
organism thing then you might have some
like you know ion channels which are
open or closed on the in on the sort of
membranes of the cells and what they do
sort of depends on the state of all of
those cells and so you have to account
for that in these morphisms but in the
monomial case where you don't have this
like
context or configuration dependence um
the morphisms become a little bit
simpler they just become like a forwards
thing so here we've got an A and an S
going forwards and we we have to figure
out a way of giving an X and in the
backwards direction we have an A and an
s on the inside and a y as well coming
in and we have to figure out a way of
giving a b and a t so this this really
just encodes the wiring of these two
boxes into the bigger box like I
said so using this category poly whose
morphisms are the dependent lenses and
objects of the polinomial we can give a
system the which um captures generative
models um I'm going to just talk about
discrete time ones in the in the
traditional Sense on the monomials but
also has some kind of more complicated
mode dependent structure um that I think
could be useful in general as well so
this is going to be an index category
like I said Maps the polinomial IE an
interface of the kind that I was just
talking about to a category whose
objects are generative models on that
interface so that means that they are
going to be a quadruple like this so
that is a state space s um I'm just
going to think of it as a set a prior on
the state space which we could think of
as like a goal or just prior beliefs
about the agent States um a likelihood
which is a sort of stochastic output
morphism
um in the case that this is um just a
monomial o y to the a then that's just
like P of O given
s and then there's also this transition
map which says okay well given that I am
in this state um I I sort of can sample
an input that has to correspond to the
um configuration that I'm in so I sample
from my pi and then okay I'm allowed to
receive an input in this corresponding
um at like configuration P of one which
is given by my likelihood and then okay
I receive an input and I've got a state
and I get a new state so that's like the
transition
function again in the sort of monomial
case this is exactly what we normally
have in active inference we have um a
state s and an action in a and we get a
new state it's just that now we're
allowed to have the possible inputs to
the system I.E the the possible actions
that you could take on this generative
model to be dependent on the state that
the system or the state that the
environment is in according to that
model um and so that that captures this
idea that you know say if I have my eyes
closed I can't like receive um you know
visual signals anymore uh or or you know
if I open my eyes then I can't so
there's a sort of difference in the sort
of input signals that I can receive or
if I'm sort of plugged into my computer
I can't sort of easily get up and walk
around because you know I might like
have to like unplug a wire or something
so there it captures this mode
dependence um there are sort of
important sort of mathematical
bookkeeping duties we have to do which
I'm not going to do but it's easy to
check that it's like functorial which
means that it's indexed in the right way
and that it's monoidal which means we
can put systems side by side and I've
only just told you what the objects of
this category gen of P are but it also
has morphisms and these are ways of like
comparing systems um that are known in
computer science as coalgebra
homomorphisms um so this captures the
notion of generative model that we're
used to in active inference but it
allows for a lot more structure um in
particular this kind of mode dependent
structure and this compositional
structure so just to sort of say like
what the kind of thing I mean by
structured interface um I'm taking an
example from computer science because um
there are a lot of uses of polinomial
Science in pols in computer science and
one of them particular this for defining
like um domain specific programming
languages um and I think that one use of
this could be for defining like
artificial agents that um behave nicely
with respect to sort of computer
interfaces and so um we can encode the
data of a s domain specific language
into a polinomial because say we've got
a little calculator language that has
like two binary operations like plus and
times they each take in an input uh take
in two inputs we've got a sort of unary
operation it just takes in one thing and
it negates it and like we've got some
constants
like uncountably many that represent the
um real numbers then we can encode the
data of this as like you know 2 y^ 2 + y
+ r because we've got these two little
operations what uh two binary operations
you've got two possible inputs one un
operation it's got one input and like
these constants which don't take any
inputs and then we can you know
represent the set of all terms of this
language as like a set by by applying
the polinomial to like some X um the
those X terms those X elements represent
the inputs and then we could think okay
well what would be um a machine that
like takes in term terms of my little
domain specific language and returns
values it's it's something like r y to
the P of X which is again another
polinomial and you can do lots of things
like this basically you can encode like
any small um programming language or any
any sort of um sort of abstract syntax
tree into a polinomial um it's not just
examples from computer science that are
relevant but they have a lot of
structure and so I wanted to show off
those examples I think you could do a
lot of things in biology as well using
this language um but it's it's kind of
more sophisticated than we can do with
just sort of a set of observations than
a set of
actions another thing that I wanted to
mention is that in this context um it's
quite natural to think of the actions or
um that that an agent takes as morphisms
in a category and this is where this
typing information or this typing idea
comes from um because you know in
categories morphisms have to compose and
so we can check that the sort of they
they they are sort of compatible when
before we compose them um and so to give
you an idea of how this works we can
think of categories as like little State
machines so here I've drawn a little
category it's got objects x y and Zed
and it's got these morphisms it's got
two morphisms from X to Y um f and f
Prime and you know we've got G from y to
zed and we can go along F and then along
G to go from X to Y to zed and that
takes us from X to zed or we can go you
know fime to Z blah blah blah but these
are like steps or paths in a little
space and so you know we go from X to Y
and then y to zed but it doesn't it sort
of doesn't make sense you know if you if
we had another object over here that
wasn't connected to zed we could go over
here but then we wouldn't immediately be
able to go over Z that's to say like if
we had an island um or a peninsula or an
island with just one Bridge onto it um
we could go onto the island but then to
go somewhere else we'd have to go back
along the
bridge sometimes the act like the places
you can go depend on where you are and
this encodes that data into into the
notion of action um and indeed every
category is itself can be turned into a
polinomial um the configurations of the
polinomial are the objects of the
category and then the the sort of inputs
to a system would be the morphisms of
that category out of each object that is
to say all the steps you could take out
of each object and then a policy would
have to be like a composable sequence of
morphisms or you know in active
inference you might have something more
stochastic so You' have a belief over
such sequences but this because you have
this typing information it means you can
check that your policies make sense like
you don't try to go somewhere and then
somewhere from that destination that
intermediate destination you don't try
to go somewhere that is not connected or
take an action that doesn't make sense
in in some other
way um and so we can use this to start
to think about um like safety of
policies um using the logic that comes
with category Theory this isn't
something that I've elaborated but I
think it's a sort of starting step to
talk about um safe active inference
systems in a very rigorous way um and I
already mentioned that other kinds of um
important notion are also morphisms in
in structured active inference like
changes of interface or changes of
structure and that means I think that we
can rigorously apply AC of inference to
itself to do things like um structure
learning or to to choose how you you
know like connect yourself into a bigger
unit like into an
organization um and on that note let me
tell you about how in this setting we
talk about systems that manage systems
um this is a generalization or will
become a generalization of what is known
in the active inference literature as D
for hierarchical active
inference um and so the sort of formal
Gadget that we use to talk about this is
known as the closure of the category of
interfaces that is to say it has what's
known as an internal H H because
morphism is otherwise known as
homomorphism um and the category of
polinomial and also the category of
lenses um has one of these internal homs
that is a way to refer to the category
within
itself um and that internal H has to be
given a polinomial form and so the sort
of configurations of this polinomial are
the from say from P to Q they are the
ways of wiring P into Q I.E the set of
lenses from P to
q and then you know we have to give as
well exponents to provide a polinomial
and these Pol these exponents are going
to be all the sort of data that the
input to these um to these sort of P
systems if we think of the p as like the
inner systems that they require and so
they require outputs from p and inputs
from q and that's exactly what this like
input data is here so if we so we've got
a polinomial that represents how P's
Connect into q's and we can think about
what uh generative models would be over
such a polinomial that is like um
systems that control the wiring of PS
into Q's or as I've done in this example
control the wiring of a P1 and a P2 into
q and so what would these systems be
well they would observe the outputs of
P1 and P2 and then the inputs of Q and
they would update their states
accordingly having made these
observations and then they would output
ways to connect P1 and P2 into q and
that really is like what a manager does
in an organization or sort of high level
system does in a sort of hierarchical
structure um and there's a sort of nice
fact that I'll use later on that if you
have sort of trivial inner system I.E
just with this polinomial y then the
generative models on this H polinomial
are just the same as generative models
on the outer polinomial um so we can use
this to capture not only these
hierarchical systems but just kind of
regular systems as well
um uh there's an interesting or you know
sort of side fact or reason why this is
known as a closed structure is that this
is the same as something that's known in
computer science as currying um you
might have seen this that if you have a
function that takes like inputs in A and
B and produces C like this is Maps a B
to like f of A and B we could also write
this as like a function that maps from a
to maps from B to C and that says okay
well this Maps a to F of a something
which is a map from B to C so this is
the same idea it says okay well the like
ways of like mapping into this P
polinomial are the same as like mapping
of the joint systems um it's an
important structure that gets used a lot
in this
context okay so I spent a lot of time
talking about structured generative
models in particular you know I
introduce this hierarchical structure
and I talked about um the structure of
you know mode dependence in a sort of
abstract and general way um but it was
always about generative models and I
haven't really talked much about like
doing um action selection or State
inference um which is of course a very
important part of active inference and
in some senses kind of what active
inference is all
about um but but those
processes fit very naturally into the
same framework um there's something that
you attach to a generative model active
inference always starts from a
generative model and
then describes the process for providing
a policy to control it and so an active
INF agent or I think an agent more
generally is made up of two things it's
made up of the generative model and then
something that I call a controller which
um basically chooses the policy to
provide to the generative model it's a
way to sort of take this generative
model which is an open
system and like s of me sort of render
it closed it of takes the observations
that are produced by the generative
model and then turns them into actions
that can go into the generative model
and so there's some sort of nice Duality
between the genor model and the
controller and it's this Duality that
allows us to formalize um active
inference in a nice compositional way um
one way I sort of started to like to
think about this and I don't really know
much about this subject so I I won't
make any claims that it's rigorous or
sensible but I think of the sort of
generative model as somehow like the
consciousness of the agent it represents
how the agent perceives the world and
then the policy part is it's sort of the
subconscious processes which Drive the
agent in that gen to model I mean this
is just sort of my my thinking I don't
know if it's if it's very sensible um
but as I say we can fit all of this into
the same framework um by by kind of
taking poly and this category of
generative models and the home structure
and sort of putting them all together
into um a sort of nice bundle or nice
mix so I have this two category called
gen poly um made up of all these
ingredients the objects are the
interfaces the polinomial um you can
think of them as generalized Markoff
blankets and then now it's a two
category so instead of between one
object and another having a set of
morphisms now we have a whole category
of morphisms so we have both one cells
and two cells so it's a two-dimensional
structure um but the H category from P
to Q is just the systems on the H
interface so that is um generative
models on the structure interface that
sort of takes P systems and turns them
into Q systems so they're sort of
hierarchical manager systems and then
the the two cells are ways of compose of
comparing these systems and I haven't
really talked much about that and they
won't they won't feature much in in this
talk and they don't feature in the paper
either um but they're important if we
want to talk about things like structure
learning or logic and then the
composition of systems is as I've been
saying all along we take a system over
over one sort of h polinomial and a
system over another H polinomial and
then we wire them together so then we
have like a sort of high level manager
here and a sort of lower level manager
and they talk to each other to produce
what we could think of as like a
hierarchical organization which takes
sort of very lowlevel things and turns
them into high level things
um and yeah so we're out to tens of
polinomial and that makes this um gen
poly 2 category into a monoidal 2
category so we put systems side by side
in the way you'd
expect um and it means we can draw um uh
an active inference system in this kind
of string diagram way that category
Theory people like um so the generative
model is this is is like something like
this it takes in nothing and it produces
T things that is produces uh well I
guess this is a bir directional thing so
it sort of is a a morphism from a
trivial object into p and it produces P
outputs and takes P inputs and then the
policy is like it's dual so it takes in
P inputs and it produces what the
generative model expects as
output and then as I uh may have
mentioned that no I didn't mention yet
um that this this as I've said before at
least in the case of just a single
system just on P um the home from y to P
is just the same as P so that's good
this captures um what I was saying
before about generative models on an
interface and then the the the the
controller is a is a model from P to Y
that means it doesn't sort of it
produces a sort of closed system when
you compose it with p and that is that
is to capture this picture that I drew
before where you have like um a box
which is the gener model which is open
and then this controller which sort of
closes it off and that's encoded in this
of
formality okay and so now we've got this
definition the the controller of of a
generative model is like being dual to
it um we can sort of unwind or
decompress what that means um
mathematically um so the home polinomial
from P to Y has this form it's just
something that you can you can work
through if you write down that
expression and figure out what it means
um the outputs or configurations of this
polinomial are what are known as
sections of P so a section of a of this
P taken as a bundle is a way of of going
from the outputs and for each output
giving an input that that matches the
corresponding configuration so it's it's
just a way of sort of making this
diagram commute as we would say in
category theory that is to say okay we
we we're in a an output or a
configuration and we say okay well um I
need to provide an input and yes that's
nice it matches what what configuration
I'm in and we think of this as like
being the data that the world um
supplies to the system so the system uh
or like we think of the system as
producing outputs the environment takes
those outputs and then turns them into
inputs and so that's exactly what these
sections do um so those sections are the
things that are outputed by this policy
part and then the inputs to the policy
part are the outputs produced by the P
system and so as I say it's exactly dual
so the outputs are the things that the
the inputs that P needs and the inputs
are the things that P produces and so we
can unravel this in the case of um this
monomial interface which is going to
give us what we get in classical Act of
inference um the output path of one of
these systems is going to do action
selection ction so it it has a little
State space which I just called R here
um it takes an observation and it
produces an action and this is um
exactly what the the sort of action
selection part process and active
inference does it takes a state and an
observation it produces an action that
is to be taken in the Gen model and it
also has this part which does um State
inference or you might see it called the
recognition model or it computes the
basian posterior over the states so
we're in a state and we have an
observation and then we get a new
state so that that this these these
thing these sort of four things these
two parts of the the the policy system
and then the the transition model and
the likelihood in the generative model
are basically all of what an active
inference system is you might include
the prior in that as well I suppose um
and and so that means that we've got all
the data of an active inference system
in this very neat little package it's a
generative model and it's dual and
that's kind of
it um there are obviously some like um
ways you can extend this and not that's
not something I'm doing in this paper in
this talk but basically you can do
things like consider trajectories over
actions or continuous time models or do
lots of other things like this um but
I'm going to try to keep it as simple as
I can I know I've introduced a lot of
mathematical detail so
far and then okay so then there are
three further generalizations that kind
of crop up pretty immediately from this
this um that I think are quite important
and I want to just introduce to you all
um the first of them is that you know
now we've got this home
structure
um and this nice kind of uh two category
we can think about um as I've indicated
already think about hierarchical or deep
systems and that really corresponds to
nesting small systems in bigger systems
and that you know formally means going
from um generative models with sort of
trivial inner boundary to generator
models which have a sort of non-trivial
inner boundary and now unfortunately
I've swapped my direction of my home so
it goes from Q to P um the story still
holds I've just change p and Q round um
and I I'll say in a moment like how this
un unwind so you can get a sense of what
it does and then we do the same to the
policy it just does the same thing in
the opposite direction now it's a system
from P to
q but they're still like dual so the
intuition is still they're still good I
think um that's one thing we can do um
this produces uh a a uh a sort of by
category a two category or what we
ultimately becomes a double category um
where the the arrows are pairs of a
system and a
controller
um and uh of the next thing we can do to
this is to think about how do we model
in a sort of rigorous way the changes of
model changes of interface that I
introduced at the beginning um that
corresponds to adding yet another
dimension to this structure um and that
formally encodes changes the model as
extra morphisms categorically and that
makes them kind of accessible to this
formalism um not something that I'm
going to talk about today uh because I
introduced enough stuff here um just to
sort of wet your appetite I think um but
um in this formalism even in this sort
of just sort of two-dimensional
setting because it's quite General
because it it it says that active
inference is is really made up of two
key ingredients a system and a
controller um it allows us to ask
precisely how active inference relates
to other theories of agency or other the
system and of course lots of people have
thought about the relationship between
active inference and other accounts like
reinforcement learning um but I think
this framework allows us to make those
uh relationships very very precise
indeed and to say okay well you there is
say one might hope uh a particular like
possibly Universal way of mapping any
reinforcement learning system into an
active inference system in a
compositional way so that is you could
do it for the parts and also for the
like complex system and you get
something that makes
sense um and possibly one could go and
and I think it's quite likely that one
could also go in the other direction and
there would be nice sort of we we might
expect like nice formal um results like
these two processes were adjoint or
something like that um but I I would
like to highlight at this point that
active inference I think in this setting
is really not just one um theory of
agency but really it's a whole family of
theories of agency parameterized by
things like whether or not you take
continuous time or discrete time systems
because those of course give you
different systems theories or whether
you do Planning by sophisticated
inference or inductive inference or just
one time step or whether you
um or whether you think about like
multiple time steps or whether you take
the expected free energy or the free
energy of the expected future so there
are all these different variations and
they give you like different like
Notions of active inference and so
probably different theories of agency in
this sense
um and and I think that's important for
like making sense of the whole active
inference landscape and in particular
the sort of um landscape of theories of
agency itself because it means that we
can have like a nice rigorous map of all
of these things and like connect them
from you know from um you know connect
one thing into another quite nicely
um again I'm not going to say very much
about this but I I just wanted to Sag it
up that that's something that you get
out of making precise these
structures so I I mentioned that I
wanted to highlight how this captures um
deep or hierarchical act of
inference um and this this happens in I
think quite a a natural way I mean I've
introduced an awful lot of formalism
here but once you get used to it I think
it works okay um
that hierarchical act of inference just
corresponds to a sequence of composite
arrows in this two category that whose
arrows are made up of you know a uh a
generative model and uh control dra is
upside down but it doesn't
matter um so in this setting again as
I've mentioned the monomial interfaces
correspond to the kind of normal Mark of
blankets that are just made made up of a
set of observations and a set of actions
um but we get this hierarchical
structure in the one cells of this um
two
category and if we think of the sort of
composition in this two category is
basically by nesting then you know we
could I sort of draw it schematically
like this um I I'm indexing like the
higher levels the sort of interior
levels of the system as like higher in
this set in this context so like i+ one
is kind of more inside the system than I
um often that corresponds to like a
higher level of like explanation in
active inference um but because there's
this Duality between like um the
generative model and the the controller
or the policy part I don't I don't like
to say high level or lowlevel because it
gets confusing I prefer to sort of think
about how deep you are inside your agent
and how so or close you are to the
exterior world when I'm talking about
the direction of this of this kind of
comp of this kind of hierarchy and so to
the left we go sort of more interior and
to the right we go more exterior and
these arrows Point sort of in the
exterior Direction like this and so a s
of hierarchical active inference system
goes from interior to exterior it's a
sort of uh it's an arrow of this kind
that un unwinds to this the following
data it's a a state f a likelihood that
is you know parameterized by the state
and the interior um belief about
observations so of which you could think
of as like high level in in some context
observations and it produces a a
prediction about the more exterior
observations there's a prior on um the
in more interior actions which again you
could possibly think of as high level
but this is parameterized by the or
conditioned on the state and the and the
sort of interior observations and the
exterior um uh sort of more exterior
actions um or the system's belief about
the more exterior actions and then a
transition model which again depends on
the actions taken at this kind of
exterior level sort of high LEL in this
case this is the of high level actions
and it gives us uh new State on the
basis of the Old State and then there's
this other part which is dual which is
the controller so the control here I've
written the the state space is like
beliefs over the over the generative
model State space so that says it takes
um it has this again these three parts
so one is like a generative process
which takes the in the sort of exterior
observations the um the signals which
impinge on the on the sort of outer mark
of blanket and translates them onto the
inner Mark of
blankets so goes in the other direction
like
this um there's a sort of policy part
which does Action selection so it takes
in a belief over the state space and um
like a high level or a more interior
belief about over the actions and it
produces um what we could think of as a
more exterior uh choice of action so
that could be like passing down
a sort of high level motor signal um
into like lowlevel sequence of like
muscle contractions because I think of
the sort of closer to the exterior
systems as like the ones being made of
of lots of say cells um rather than the
the the interior model of myself as just
a a body with arms that
move and then finally there's this
component which does um basian inference
over the states it takes in a state and
an exterior observation that is the
signals which they impinge on my retina
and it updates the internal State and
that's you know the part that does like
um you know that gives you your
posterior Over
States this is a lot of data um in the
literature it sometimes comes out in a
slightly less um or maybe slightly more
familiar way or a slightly less detailed
way where the you don't have the
interior
observations um which I think was like
sort of beliefs about high level patches
of information like the object rather
than the sort of individual like Ral
gangon data or something like that and
if you imagine not having these ois oi
plus
ones in this model then you wouldn't
have like this generative process um and
you would only have a likelihood which
takes a state to an observation but you
still get this like hierarchical action
selection process um so it just takes
like high level AC like high level
beliefs about sort of actions like I'm
moving my arm into sort of lower level
sort of um signals that I pass to my
muscles but I think it's nice to allow
for this um hierarchy in the opposite
direction on the observations as
well okay so the final thing I want to
mention is that um the categorical
systems theory lets us talk about um
let's us use categorical Logic for
talking about um goals and uh behaviors
of systems and formally it's quite easy
to say what we need to do that it's not
something that I've done because
actually a lot of details but formly
like it's relatively simple all you need
is the ability to Define what's known as
a vibration and a vibration is just like
a collection of things indexed by this
other thing so again the sort of index
category thing Notions I introduced at
the beginning is uh basically equivalent
to vibrations but the idea is now that
over each system we have a vibration of
um of predicates of logical statements
about those
systems um that it's indexed by the
systems and the systems are indexed by
interfaces and it's compatible with all
the changes of system and changes of
interface and things like that um but
one notion one sort of simple idea of
like logical structure or predicate you
might attached to systems is just notion
of um goal for a system so these priors
on the state space um and I haven't
elaborated this um but you know once
you've got this we can kind of use the
structures of category Theory to do
things like Define quantifiers or
logical connectives and soort of build
up statements about goals out of sort of
sort of more primitive statements and
compare systems goals and to say
possibly things like oh now if I've got
a bunch of systems connected
together um maybe that they work
together to acheve AI their goal
possibly like by some process of
consensus um this allows us to talk
about that kind of thing in a
mathematically rigorous way or now we've
got this formal logic to talk about um
the goals of systems can we use this to
talk about Notions of safety or to
guarantee that um the goals will be
achieved within certain bounds or um
that they won't try to do this why this
thing or this other thing which we don't
like um I think this is important again
as I've mentioned at the beginning for
thinking about um safe artificial
systems um that's all I wanted to talk
about it was a lot um I think we can go
back and elaborate on any of this um and
uh I'm sure we'll come back to it in the
future as well um thank you so much for
having me I hope it wasn't too
bamboozling um but I I'm you always
willing to answer questions and if you
have more questions please feel free to
get in touch afterwards as
well thank you Toby
wow okay yeah while people are asking
some questions in live chat which I'll
read to you could you reiterate how does
what you refer to as classic active
inference with Markov blanket basian
graphical formalism how does that
overall literature relate to what you
discussed today in terms of Applied
category
Theory right okay so I think um the very
concise way way of putting it let me see
if I can go back to a slide where it's
um relatively well not too intimidating
the concise way putting it is that
um the systems in active inference that
I like classical that we're more
familiar with um here to for are
basically like sub Theory or a
subcategory of this whole structure that
is spanned we would say in mathematics
by these monomial inter spaces um these
are the ones that don't have this like
complicated um State dependence on the
actions they just have a space of
possible observations and a space of
actions um and in particular if you
don't think about like these
hierarchical or deep systems then it's
relatively simple to see that those
system those kind of generative models
are captured by this formalism um
because you get uh you know on over one
of these mon omals the monomial
represents the mark of blanket um the uh
coefficient here is the observations the
exponent is the actions um we have a
state space we have a prior we have a
likelihood and we have a transition
model and that's kind of the whole deal
with a generative model um the the sort
of policy part the thing that I call the
controller excuse me um is is is it kind
of s like I said uh it's it's the thing
that's dual it it does um let's see if I
can go back to the slide it does
uh yeah it does Action selection I.E
planning and it does Bas in inference um
I.E it produces the posterior here R is
just like a placeholder usually this at
least in the story that I've told in the
paper this would be like beliefs Over
States D here means
distributions um so this is
distributions Over States
um it's just a way of like packaging all
of that up into a kind of nice
compositional
framework so that we can because you see
a lot of you know if you look at
complicated hierarchical active
inference um pictures they often have
like really complicated structure but
actually these
structures typically have like some kind
of common repeating elements um that in
principle should just be able to be
boxed up and repeated and plugged in in
a nice way that is mathematically sound
and reusable and kind of uh you know I
like category Theory because it's a kind
of linger franer and and it means that
you don't have like small variations in
formalism like what does message passing
mean well it means lots of different
things lots of different people um in
this setting you have you you can be
very precise about like what your theory
of agency is um what the notion of Mark
of blanket is one of the things I often
find a bit tricky about um the active
inference literature is the notion of
Mark of blanket is quite is it's kind of
intuitively quite easy to graph um but
in this kind of dynamical setting it
doesn't quite
correspond um to the notion of Marco
blanky that originally came out of
Statistics um
un unless you do some kind of Maneuvers
that unwind your Dynamics into a big
like uh um graphical model and like draw
certain boxes around some repeating
elements then then you can say that the
mark of blanket of the system is the uh
the parents children co-parents like you
would say in
statistics but it's it's kind of not
really what the job of the mark of
blanket is um not in active inference
and not in statistic they sort of play
different roles an active inference the
mark blanket is the agent's interface
it's like the boundary of the agent how
it interacts with the world and I think
it's nice to be precise about that it's
nice to say that what when we say markco
blanket we mean interface and our
interfaces come together and they can
connect up and they can produce bigger
systems with interfaces um and that has
a particular grammar to it which is not
the same as the the grammar of markup
blankets and statistics um it might be
in certain cases but if we want to talk
about the sort of whole world of
different kinds of dynamical systems
from these discrete time ones that I was
talking about to various different
models of continuous time ones then it's
it's not it's not so easy to make the
connection back to mark of blanket and
so I think to some people who come from
statistics um this terminology is can be
a bit confusing and one of the things
that comes out of this structured Act of
inference is that it it says hey this is
how we can be precise about this um it
says okay well we have this n of
interface it can be whatever you want as
long as it's you know it behaves like we
think of as interface and I've just told
you about one story of interfaces and
and basically one story of systems like
over the interface but categorical
systems theory is very very general it
lets you talk about lots of different
kinds of interface lots of different
kinds of systems and this is why I think
that this story of structured active
inference whilst it captures the kinds
of active inference systems that we're
familiar with it's really a theory of
the structure of Agents generally and I
think active inference wants to be that
um and that's why I think that you know
here we might want to expect that
there's like tradition there's like um
canonical ways of relating other
theories of agency to active inference
or to a particular flavor of active
inference and that we can make those
mappings precise precise not just for an
individual model or an individual system
but for all systems of a particular kind
um and and that's the kind of
universality that I think we should be
aiming for um I can explain what these
arrows on this page mean but I don't you
know I think you get the idea that like
this is to say if you've got an agent
it's a system on a controller you can
like forget the controller and you've
just got a system active inference is a
way of saying okay given my system I've
got a story about how to attach
controllers to it how to do policy uh
how to do planning how to do action
selection how to do state inference
active inference is a recipe to take
your generative model and provide you a
controller and reinforcement learning is
a or the the variants of reinforcement
learning are also recipes for doing
something similar um so it's a sort of
mapping in the other
direction so I think the thing to take
away is that you know if you're just
interested in simple models um with like
one set of actions and one set of
observations then you don't have to
worry about this but if you're
interested in building big complex
models of big complex systems like
organizations or if you're interested in
talking about systems whose interfaces
can be dependent or whose like actions
might depend on where they are or what
they're doing or who can change their
interfaces or who can come together to
form organizations that themselves are
like dynamical and changing then we need
stronger mathematical tools for
describing those systems and those
processes and those kinds of agents and
that's what this framework and that's
what categorical system Theory gives
us awesome so so many great points and
things I'll just highlight two pieces
that I think really hit you called it a
particular grammar that knowingly or
unknowingly plays on the particular
partition splitting things into
particles and being that partitioning
and this is also a grammar of particles
and it's a particular grammar like there
are sentences that are syntactically or
grammatically correct so that's this
kind of like syntactic level of typing
there are certain Expressions within the
active inference ontology or grammar
that would be syntactically valid or not
or would be examples of an instance or
an existential claim or have these other
kinds of statuses and then also there's
this sort of
conceptual connection that is the
semantics that separates from the strong
typing of the syntax so it it brings up
a lot of linguistic and then also you
said it's a recipe for for how to do
action and that is like if we were to do
dynamical systems modeling of a predator
prey system or of temperature in a room
but then to bring in the upstairs
control section can open up multiple
possible like cascading State space
ramifications especially if you allow
for the heading in and out of the nested
system that opens a lot of dependencies
that at least need to be accounted for
or just go with a special case where
it's nothing other than just like a
fixed situation which is kind of where
the buck stops ultimately for any hyper
hyper hyper
prior yeah I I I like I like those
Reflections so I think um yeah there's a
this like particles idea you know I Tred
to sort of capture very feeble way I'm
not very good at drawing like you've got
this kind of nesting of systems um and
I'm trying to capture that in this
formalism um
so you could think of like these like
outer the outer boundary as being like
as I say your body's boundary or like
the boundary of like a whole
organization or Society or something
like that or ecosystem and then the the
sort of outer like the job of the outer
system is like to pass messages into the
inner parts which are like your organs
or the sort of units of a organization
or departments or something like that or
sort of lower so we often think of a
lower level but like they're more like
smaller scale or more like Interior
Systems um one thing that's not so easy
is to talk about like the sort of birth
and death of these things I haven't
really thought much about like how
systems are like created from others but
I'm I'm trying to like get at least some
framework for talking about like what it
means to be one um before we talk about
how to like split them up um you said
some things about grammar um yes and I
think it's it's I'm trying to use this
very sort of um in some sense quite like
sparse mathematical grammar of category
Theory um but I've tried to do so in a
way that as I say is like is is quite is
quite General and it kind of ends up
being inherently kind of you know a bit
kind of alien um but I think the the
thing you gain from that is this kind of
um you know ability to talk about lots
of different kinds of thing um and
hopefully um you this is just the
beginning of this project that it
becomes you know you know we get tools
and stories for how to you express
things in this kind of language um it's
it's I think most suited for trying to
understand like
complex systems um so as I say I think
if you're if you're happy with just like
normal active inference then it's
probably
fine great and also I'm wearing an
appropriate embroidered onion shirt on
the birth and death even though from
each nucleuses or cores perspective it
is like being at the center of a
Bullseye from where it is taking another
view might look more like a chocolate
chip cookie or like multiple nested
organs so it's it's not that it's like
just a bullseye even though that's just
the two layers that's just the motif of
nesting and then when you described how
the systems can be put side by side then
you could have a situation where it's
like the cookie has two chocolate chips
and then the next time step there's a
third one but it's disconnected so it's
the island and then another kind of
actor comes in and changes the wiring
secondarily so one I wanted to I haven't
really talked about at all but one thing
I want to be able to talk about and it's
kind of related to this question of like
when the systems like dissolve into
other systems or how can we see things
as like uh you know a chocolate chip
cookie or a bulla or something like this
um or you know how do we you know or a a
group of trees or a forest or something
um you know this is this this thing it
reduces systems in you know it's
category Theory so it turns systems into
arrows
um but really this structure like wants
to be what's known as a a double
category so here we would the arrows
would be like the changes of interface
and then we would maybe have like some
other structure down here which
represents another system and we could
then then we have like what are known as
squares and these squares would
represent how we could see like this
like this system up here as a composite
or as a different kind of system how we
could see the the forest as trees or
something like that um so it allows us
to represent these kinds of like you
know dissolving or these kinds of
changes I haven't explained in detail
how this works but it's a step towards
that kind of process yeah cool and then
of course all the great jux positions
with more topologically stabile systems
uh neural networks and then more like
the ant nestmates
okay I'll ask a question from the Live
Chat math for wisdom wrote I wonder if
it is possible to interpret it in the
opposite way that the policy is the
Consciousness so in that little
speculation yeah what what led you to to
see or identify one with the
other yeah because really I I always
found the generative model encapture
encapsulates like the world as I
perceive it there nothing really that I
can do to change like we we think of so
the generative model is a system yeah so
there's one peculiarity about this which
is that
um the key ingredient is like a system
whose outputs are
observations and that seems a bit weird
sometimes to me and it may seem weird to
people who used to active inference
where you could think of the the outputs
of an agent truly be the actions but the
the the the generative model I the the
agent beliefs about the world is a
dynamical system which outputs
observations so the agent receives and
so that that seems like the wrong way
around but it it it's just how the
mathematics requires it to be and
so it this thing being so like crucial
in the structure says to me that like
this is like the sort of this is you
know when we see you know of inference
text is often like s uh given o and m so
it's like conditioned on a particular
kind of model this this gamma is M and
like this m doesn't typically change an
active rence unless it's by some like
process of evolution for an individual
agent this model is fixed and it this
this thing it like represents like
everything that I see and it and it it
it represents how I expect the World to
Change given the actions I take and it's
like it is in ter say it's the agent's
world the agent there in active
inference there is no like the agent
can't access what the real world is like
only has the generative model and so
that's why I think this is like this is
like my world this is like my conscious
experience and then so what actions I
take I mean maybe so maybe this includes
some self model and I think you know I'm
doing planning or I think I'm you know
behaving in a way that's reasoned but
actually of acting on Instinct according
to these subconscious processes I mean I
don't know much about Consciousness
science but I think that that kind of
story is
possible and so this stuff seems to be
the things that I don't necessarily
directly experience in the same way that
I directly experience like my visual
signals um but they are the things that
make me like me they are the things that
provide my input to the world um and
again yeah that's all like Dynamics and
it's maybe stuff that I observe but
maybe I only observe it because it forms
like an interior part of this model
which might have some complex structure
of the kind that I was talking about um
so that's why I thought of it that way
around um and of course like you know
maybe there is some deliberative
planning process or like you know some
internal like reasoning that goes on in
my conscious experience and I do have an
inner monologue and often it does seem
like that so I think that there is some
like
interplay between these but possibly I
think that stuff is borne out by having
some complex structure in this rather
than in these like things that I think
of a subconscious processes like I don't
I
don't I don't like experience my like
own Bas and inference processes except
in the cases that they go wrong like or
like I have some illusion like sometimes
I've gone into sometimes I'm in a
building that's particularly symmetrical
and I go out of like a a list then I go
into one place and I'm on the wrong side
and it all feels really weird like but
that's that's not like the same kind of
cons that's kind of unusual experience
anyway that that's that's my feeling
there what an inusual experience I I'll
read from math wisdom he wrote I think
that makes sense and now I understand
the distinction better the generative
model creates beliefs the policy creates
actions but our actions are faded we are
only free to choose our beliefs our
Consciousness has to do with the beliefs
we take our will did I understand the
distinction
correctly I think so I think that sounds
like a good good way of putting it I
mean this is this is really just my
basically this is like my armchair
philosophizing I don't know I mean it
would be nice if this matched like what
people think is actually going on but
it's just what the sort of mathematics
seem to be saying to me at
least towards the applied side what
kinds of of programming languages or
approaches or open- Source software or
methods can people use to start
exploring
this that is a great question and you
know what at the moment that doesn't
have a great answer the best
answer for now is that I mean at least
for like modeling is that in juliia
um the guys at the topos Institute have
been producing a collection of packages
in the sort of Mia of their project
algebraic Julia which is all about
representing categorical structures and
um doing compositional modeling in in
Julia um but Julia itself is not like
necessarily well suited to describing
things describing the world in this
in this particular kind of compositional
way it has its nice compositional
features but basically in algebra Julia
they've written like a little like
sublanguage in Julia itself that encodes
these categorical structures um one of
the things that's quite nice about
category theory is that it's very like
you know it's about composition and so
it's very modular and it gives you a lot
of things that you can change
um I'll let me go back to where I talked
about um systems theory right at the
very beginning yeah so you know I just
write down this arrow and it maps from
like my category of interfaces to the
category of categories and in in
principle I could just this should be
like a little program which takes in
which where I just like write I provide
it with a polinomial and it gives me
back this other data structure um this
category of systems um and then I should
yeah I could I I should be able to talk
about morphisms between these things and
I could be a map like this or make like
changes to this and have my computer
automatically do it um but that's just
not possible with any kind of
computational tools that we have right
now um and I often feel that it should
be possible to do this in a way that's
not necessarily like tied to a single
programming language like like alge
Julia is to Julia there are also like
dependently type programming languages
for like proof assistance but if you
write in those then you're stuck in that
world one of the things that's nice
about like the worldwide web is
that these days you can write into lots
of languages and they get compiled to
web assembly and we can interact in a
sort of language agnostic way and this
this mathematics should be language
agnostic but we don't have any languages
or tools for talk about it yet um it's
something that I think should change uh
people who are interested in Chang here
it should like talk to the topest people
talk to me and I would like to see it I
would like to see tools which are really
nicely compositional and people as I say
the topest people are working on it
they're building other things in Rust um
those are the best answers I know of for
now but they're not like
Optimal thank you well it's an optimal
agenda so that's very cool and to be
able to connect even potentially in the
coming months between the algebraic
Julia and RX INF fur. JL could already
off for some cool opportunities yes I
think that would be a great project cool
um over the last years like working on
this from your dissertation which we
discussed in the live stream 54 series
all the other fun and learnings that
we've had um how have you seen like the
process of going about that
recipe evolve from like the chapter 6 in
the 2022 textbook how do you feel like
as more and more of the applied category
Theory developments are formalized and
then also like operationalized how is
that trajectory of like what it looks
like to apply active
inference yeah I think it's it's been
very interesting and very exciting I
would say for a long time I I was also
like quite I guess relatively confused
about things um in some way and this is
a thing that like this is um something
that I haven't yet been able to resolve
uh and and I'm sure some people will
know how it could be resolved um but I'm
just not yeah one of them which is that
active inference has come out of a sort
of free energy principle world where
the idea is that actions are selected in
like the same kind of way that you do
perceptual inference by like minimizing
surprise or free energy um but the sort
of formal yeah so there the formal
structure of uh like pure perceptual
inference is it has a similar feeling
right so it has something that goes from
like it f like inside to outside and
then something that like goes back this
is like the thing that does
prediction or and then this is the thing
that like does you
inference
um and so this structure of these two
things you
know you by no surprise obviously has
this similar bidirectional feel but I
haven't yet shown that this action
selection process is exactly of the same
type as Basin inference of perception
and I would like it to be it's it's kind
of frustrating to me that so I thought
for a long time how do I get action when
I was writing my thesis how do I get
action into this um and that's what this
project really has been about it's like
getting action into the story finally um
but the relationship between them isn't
as neat as I would like and so um if
anybody wants to talk about that I'm
always interested in trying to like show
that like action selection really is a
kind of like surprise minimization or
approximate inference um so far it's
only kind of vaguely in the structure um
and this reminds me of something that I
wanted to say in response to your
remarks at the end when when I just
finished Daniel
um that I've said here
roughly like the data of an active
inference like a hierarchical active
inference system it has these components
it's got like a likelihood model a
transition model A you know policy thing
a state inference thing and you know
maybe it's got this like generative
process part and this action prior part
as well um but this is all just
structure this is structured active
inference this all just about structure
none of this yet is about like how do
you actually choose this likelihood or
how do you actually do like action
selection or how do you actually do
state inference um the stuff that I was
doing in the work that I was doing in my
thesis was about various different ways
that we actually do inference like
particularly um inference in the brain
using the variational inference under
the llast
approximation um but what one want well
like what I want at least is to say that
act of inference or a particular flavor
of active inference is like in some
sense Universal and that means that
there is like a canonical choice for a
given system so like we assume that
somebody comes along and gives you the
data of your generative model it could
be you Daniel or it could be like
Evolution science or something like that
and then it says okay well active says
there's a canonical way of choosing
actions that is like as optimal as you
can be and there's a canonical way of
doing inference that is as optimal as
you can be um and this story that I've
told doesn't is agnostic to that um I'm
you know a lot of people have spent time
saying here are proposals um this
framework although being agnostic allows
you to State like what are known in
category Theory as universal properties
and so those are ways of saying that
this is in some sense canonical or
optimal in some like mathematically
precise way and it would be nice to like
have the those stories about the
universality of active inference I the
ways of spelling out these functions um
to be expressed in that language um yeah
so so yeah that's that's my answer two
answers one was about this annoying
thing with inference and here about the
universality yeah there's so much to go
into and you mentioned like duel a lot
and the interface can be seen it's like
two onions where you could peel off the
interface and Associate it with one but
that would be a symmetry break because
you could also see it as being peeled
off with the other because it's an
interface and this gets into like
systems engineering what what is the
interface and
uh it's very interesting topic so I'll
see if anyone else has any final
questions like what are your next steps
on the research how do you see it being
applied and
continued okay right so my next steps
are really to produce uh longer or more
detailed paper about this than the
abstract that is available at the moment
um in particular the Abra that's
available at the moment it doesn't
really spell out uh some of this stuff
uh in particularly nice detail like um
to keep things as simple as I could I
didn't really explain like how you can
have this kind of um mode dependence
transition model as as that that is
stochastic as well as having uh
likelihoods that are sarcastic for
technical reasons it's a lot easier if
you just have the outputs of your
systems be deterministic this notation
right like sum with a sampling is is not
something that is um I I think um
conical or widely known so I'd have to
spell that out so there are lots of like
mathematical details but that's like the
first thing um and the second thing I
think is to get people using this
framework um actually talk about
building complex systems or actually
building tools for building complex
system using it um and relating those to
you know the the tools that people
already use for doing that kind of thing
like um PDP or just like you said Daniel
RX and th um it would be great to like
actually turn this into something that
people can use rather than just the
mathematical Theory I like this although
it's kind of um often people think it's
quite an alien language uh because it's
unfamiliar but it is in some ways quite
ergonomic it it's quite demanding
because it because to like prove that
something is an index category you have
to check all of these annoying
conditions and by God they are often
really really annoying and I would love
you know as a test case for this to
build like uh an artificial proof
assistant or like system that can help
me do these
checks because as I said like doing a
doing policy like action selection um is
very much like choosing a series of
morphisms and it's well known in
mathematics that proof is also choosing
a series of morphisms so I'm pretty sure
that we can use this for doing things
like proof in a way that's nicer than
large language models um so once we've
got tools I want to like actually start
applying them to things um complicated
structured models that you know are
probably beyond the systems that we have
right now
okay the Toby signal has gone out um
I'll ask one more question from the Chat
math wisdom wrote Toby it sounds like
you want to set up a free funter so that
suggests considering the adjoint funter
what is it that you want to forget if he
could Define a funter what he wants to
forget then mathematically that could
yield the funter that freely optimally
constructs the canonical way to choose
the action or do the
inference yeah what do I want to forget
in some sense what I want to forget is
like all the stuff that I might have
learned that confuses
me um but the thing is it's very hard to
distinguish the stuff that is confusing
from the stuff that is not confusing
until you've done all the work so it may
be the case that you have to construct
that ad joint in order to see that
you've got the forgetful function in the
first place U and that's unfortunately I
think the situation that I'm in um part
a lot of this process I think has really
been about um figuring out the essence
of these systems like in before it was
like approximate inference in the brain
and here it's like the essence soort the
structure of active inference um really
distilling it down into something quite
abstract
um and really just to say something
about forgetful funes um this
uh where has it gone yeah this Arrow
here that goes from Agents the category
of Agents which has these biral gen
model policy things as it's morphisms
and just goes down to systems this is a
forgetful functor it forgets the
controller the thing that is the policy
and um possibly hopefully the the way to
see active inference as universal is to
say that it's like um adjoint in a
particular way or at least it has like
at least it is a section we would say of
this thing um so yeah it's true what I'm
trying to do is find out what those ad
joints are um but it's it's hard to know
what to forget until you forgotten it
and then it's gone I don't
know you don't know what you got till
it's gone then there's the
reconstructed the reconstructed trace
and our Niche is becoming increasingly
capable from a perception and action
standpoint which is bringing up so many
fascinating topics so do you have any
final
comments not today I'm sure there'll be
other opportunities Daniel I hope so at
least I do too it's been a pleasure
thank you Toby this was an awesome
presentation it's like big structural
Evolution and development in otive
inference and so there's so many pieces
for people to to pick up and and work in
all ways developing like the background
needed to get to some of these Cliffs
and then the better structures to jump
off them
with yeah please everybody get in touch
if you have questions or projects in
mind I'm always interested to hear them
cool and I hope that we can like
reactivate some category Theory
ACM in the RX and fur project or in some
other Standalone project I'm sure it'll
happen so thank you cool peace Toby
thanks everybody in the live chat Cheers
Cheers e